jobs.nhs.uk 2018-08-10

# NHS Jobs - Privacy Statement

## Definitions

'We' / 'Us' means the NHS Business Services Authority which provides NHS Jobs via its contractor Jobsite UK (Worldwide) Limited.

## Links to Other Sites

This site contains links to other sites. We are not responsible for the privacy practices or the content of those sites.

## Collection of Personal Information

Your data will be processed to support the recruitment process for vacancies that can be found on the NHS Jobs website. This will be in accordance with the Data Protection Act 2018 (DPA), the General Data Protection Regulation (Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council (GDPR), the Regulation of Investigatory Powers Act 2000, the Telecommunications (Lawful Business Practice) (Interception of Communications) Regulations 2000, the Electronic Communications Data Protection Directive 2002/58/EC, the Privacy and Electronic Communications (EC Directive) Regulations 2003 and all applicable laws and regulations relating to Processing of Personal Data and privacy, including where applicable the guidance and codes of practice issued by the Information Commissioner.

NHS Jobs processes personal data and sensitive personal data (as described in the Data Protection Act 1998 (DPA), the EU Data Protection Directive 95/46/EC, the General Data Protection Regulation (Regulation (EU) 2016/679 of the European Parliament and of the Council (GDPR), ) to support the recruitment process to vacancies that can be found on the NHS Jobs website.

Personal data is data that relates to an identifiable living person ('data subject').

We are processing this information at your request prior to you potentially entering into a contract of employment

Special Categories of personal data we may process include:

  * Race or ethnicity
  * Physical or mental health
  * Sexual orientation and sexual life

Additional information that is considered sensitive is:

  * The commission or alleged commission of an offence, or proceedings or sentence relating to offences or alleged offences.

We and the employing organisation may be required to do this by employment law relating to access your capacity to work, to monitor that equality law is being met through the recruitment process and to comply with any safeguarding laws relating to the role you are applying for.

## Use of Your Information

By using NHS Jobs, you agree that we may collect, hold, process and use your information (including personal information) for the purpose of providing you with the NHS Jobs service and:

  * personalising your visits to NHS Jobs to improve the services provided to you;
  * informing you about the latest changes to the NHS Jobs;
  * providing customer service and support;
  * communicating (and personalising such communication) with you;
  * enabling you to share our content with others e.g. using an 'Email a friend 'or 'Share this functionality';
  * conducting market research in terms of understanding your usage of the site and how the site can improve to assist users; and/or
  * carrying out technical and statistical analysis to measure the performance of our services.

## Sharing Your Information

NHS Jobs has an interface to the Electronic Staff Record System (ESR) which is a payroll and human resources system used by most NHS organisations and by a number of other organisations providing NHS services. The data you submit to NHS Jobs may be transferred to ESR for the purposes of: establishing the human resources and payroll record; completing the recruitment process or parts of the process on ESR; or for reporting purposes such as equal opportunity monitoring.

The data you submit to NHS Jobs as part of your job application may be downloaded and transferred to the employers' own system or a third party system where an employer chooses to complete the recruitment process using a different system.

If you apply for a job on NHS Jobs then the employer which advertised the job will have access to your application and any other material you submit in support of the application for example, your accompanying CV. Employers may copy and hold some or all of this data locally in their own systems to facilitate their administration of the recruitment exercise.

An employing organisation has an obligation to inform you how they are processing your application before you apply including but not limited to:

  * automatic decision making on selection,
  * updating information the employing organisation has downloaded from NHS Jobs,
  * withdrawing an application the employing organisation has downloaded from NHS Jobs
  * how the employing organisation handles attachments that accompany the application form
  * what the employing organisation uses the Equality and Diversity data for
  * how the employing organisation handle any safeguarding concerns

An employing organisation has an obligation to provide any relevant privacy notice(s) when a request for an off line application is made.

If you have agreed to accept SMS texts these will only be sent when invited to an interview and a further (reminder) text is sent 2 days before the interview is scheduled to take place.

We will not sell or share your information for marketing purposes.

Note that summary high level data is being shared with NHS Digital for NHS vacancy monitoring purposes only.

We will not transfer your personal data outside of the European Economic Community Area.

We reserve the right to disclose your personal information to comply with applicable laws and government or regulatory bodies' lawful requests for information.

## Data retention

Job applications and adverts are retained on NHS Jobs for up to 460 days after the closing date, depending on the relevant advert's or recruitment's closing date, and then deleted. If you need to access an application form and accompanying CV/attachments or an advert and attachments relating to the vacancy, we recommend you make a copy and retain it within 400 days of the advertisement's closing date as this is the minimum period we will retain the data.

An audit log will be retained for 24 months to allow our processes to be independently checked.

## Removal of your account

If you are a jobseeker and no longer wish to retain your account on NHS Jobs then please contact the NHS Jobs Helpdesk ([help@nhs.jobs](mailto:help@nhs.jobs)) and advise them of your wish to have your account removed completely. If you have an employer's user account then please contact your organisation's system administrator directly. Please note that once the account has been deleted the data will no longer be retrievable.

## Cookies

The site uses cookies to keep track of your searches in any single visit and, once you are logged in, to identify you to the server processing your requests. The cookies will expire when you close your browser. The cookies used to identify when you are logged in do so by exchanging an encrypted code with the website server; this code will expire on the server after 60 minutes of inactivity whether or not the browser session has been closed.

A cookie is a small text file that is placed on your computer by your web browser. Cookies allow NHS Jobs to identify your computer and track details about your visit. Most browsers accept cookies automatically, but usually you can alter the settings of your browser to erase cookies or prevent automatic acceptance if you prefer. If you choose not to receive cookies from NHS Jobs, you may not be able to use some of the core features of NHS Jobs such as logging in, setting up jobs-by-email and saving your preferences.

The information collected through cookies is not personally identifiable. It only includes general information about your computer, your connection to the internet e.g. operating system and platform, IP address, NHS Jobs pages you have visited and timings of browsing on the site.

For detailed information about cookies and web beacons used on NHS Jobs and how to opt out - please visit our Cookies page.

## Keeping Your Personal Information Secure

We take the security of your personal information very seriously and have appropriate physical, technical and administrative procedures in place to help protect your personal information from unauthorised access, use or disclosure as required by law in England.

## Changes to this Privacy Notice

If we change this privacy notice, we will post the revised privacy notice here with an updated effective date. If we make significant changes to the privacy notice, we may also notify you by other means such as sending an email or posting a notice on our home page.

## Rights

The information you provided will be managed as required by Data Protection law.

You have the right to:

  * Receive a copy of the information NHS Jobs hold about you
  * Request your information be changed if you believe it was not correct at the time you provided it
  * Request that your information be deleted if you believe NHS Jobs are processing it for longer than is necessary after 25 May 2018

## Who to contact

Details of NHSBSA processing are shown on our website at <https://www.nhsbsa.nhs.uk/our-policies/data-protection>

To make use these rights or have any concerns about our professing of your information then please contact the NHSBSA Data Protection Officer:

Head of Information Governance  
NHS Business Services Authority  
Stella House  
Goldcrest Way  
Newburn Riverside  
Newcastle upon Tyne  
NE15 8NY  

You also have the right to contact the Data Protection Regulator about any concerns you may have about the use of your information. They can be contacted at:

Information Commissioner's Office  
Wycliffe House  
Water Lane  
Wilmslow  
Cheshire  
SK9 5AF

<https://ico.org.uk/global/contact-us/email/>  
<https://ico.org.uk/>
